<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: update | Glimmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://dgreen.github.io/blog/categories/update/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://dgreen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-08T18:13:52-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://dgreen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Green]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tumbling out!]]></title>
    <link href="http://dgreen.github.io/blog/2013/05/27/Tumbling-out/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-27T18:02:45-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://dgreen.github.io/blog/2013/05/27/Tumbling-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a long overdue action, I have moved the glimmer blog out of Tumblr.  I had
been wanting to use <a href="http://fletcherpenney.net/multimarkdown/">(Multi-)Markdown</a> more in blogging to continue my
focusing on the format.  I also had a student tell me he could not access the
Tumblr website at work due to its other content.  Tumblr was/is an easy to use
site but my purposes and those of other users don&rsquo;t seem to match.  I had been
looking at Jekyll for a while and considering what to try when I discovered
that GitHub supported web hosting with some support for Jekyll.  Finding the
<a href="http://jekyllrb.com/docs/migrations/">Jekyll importer</a> that would do most of the heavy lifting for
moving the site, I took the plunge.</p>

<p>Over about 4 hours, I was able to do fixups of the files that the importer
brought over.  I also changed Jekyll to use Kramdown instead of Maruku based
on  this <a href="http://natedickson.com/blog/2013/04/09/mostly-multimarkdown-blogging-in-octopress/">hint</a> originally from <a href="http://brettterpstra.com">Brett Terpstra</a>.</p>

<p>After a bit more exploring, I discovered Octopress which wraps Jekyll with
additional conveniences (even though it uses an older version of Jekyll).  I
was able to copy the raw Jekyll work into the <a href="http://octopress.org/" title="Octopress">Octopress</a> copy.</p>

<p>After trying things out, I also made the decision to host against my Github
Account rather than a project (although both Jekyll and Octopress can handle
either approach.)  This was a bit hard to retreat to.  I had to</p>

<ol>
<li> Re-run scripts</li>
<li> Edit .git/config</li>
<li> Edit Rakefile</li>
<li> Edit _config</li>
</ol>


<p>but I think I got it.</p>

<p>Most &ldquo;irritating thing&rdquo; is to put <code>bundle exec</code> in front of all rake commands
as Octopress is not using more current code.  I have not generally had to
worry about that in the past but I know many others have.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
